<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY gfdl SYSTEM "gfdl.dbk">
<!ENTITY date "November, the 2nd of 2014">
<!ENTITY version "0.6.3">
]>
<article id="index" lang="ru">
<articleinfo>
	<title>Документация Florence</title>
	<abstract role="description"><para>Этот документ описывает как установить, настроить и использовать виртуальную клавиатуру Florence.</para></abstract>
	<authorgroup>
		<author role="maintainer">
			<firstname>Франсуа</firstname>
			<surname>Agrech</surname>
			<email>f.agrech@gmail.com</email>
		</author>
	</authorgroup>
	<revhistory>
    		<revision> 
			<revnumber>0.6.3</revnumber> 
			<date>November, the 2nd of 2014</date> 
    		</revision> 
	</revhistory>
	<copyright><year>2014</year><holder>Франсуа Agrech</holder></copyright>
	<legalnotice>
		<para>Разрешается копировать, распространять и / или изменение этого документа на условиях лицензии GNU Free Documentation License, версии 1.2 или более поздней версии, опубликованной Free Software Foundation, без неизменяемых разделов, без тексты лицевых обложек, а не назад -заключения. Копия лицензии находится в разделе, озаглавленном "GNU Free Documentation License".</para>
	</legalnotice>
</articleinfo>
<indexterm><primary>florence</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>виртуальная клавиатура</primary></indexterm>
<sect1 id="intro">
	<title>Вступление</title>
	<para>Florence is an extensible scalable virtual keyboard for <ulink url="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/X_Window_System_core_protocol">X</ulink>. You need it if you can't use a real hardware keyboard, for example because of injury, handicap, your keyboard is broken or because you use a tablet PC, but you must be able to use a pointing device (as a mouse, a trackball, a touchscreen or <ulink url="http://www.inference.phy.cam.ac.uk/opengazer">opengazer</ulink>); If you can't use a pointing device, there is <ulink url="http://www.gok.ca/gok">gok</ulink>, which can be used with just simple switches.</para>
	<para>Florence не появляется, когда вам этого не нужно: она появляется на экране только тогда, когда вы имеете в этом необходимость. Основываясь на времени бездействия, автоклик доступен для инвалидов, имеющих трудности с нажатием кнопок. "Бродячий" режим - ещё один эффективный метод ввода, который может помочь</para>
	<para>Florence can be used on any desktop environment.</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="install">
	<title>Установить</title>
	<para>Make sure you have the latest version of Florence (0.6.3 as of November, the 2nd of 2014). You can get it at <ulink url="http://sourceforge.net/project/platformdownload.php?group_id=217749">Sourceforge</ulink></para>
	<sect2 id="dependencies">
		<title>Подготовка зависимостей</title>
		<para>In order to build Florence, you need a build environment with the following commands: make, scrollkeeper and a C compiler (gcc recommended), along with the following package dependencies:</para>
		<orderedlist>
			<listitem><para><ulink url="http://www.gtk.org/download-linux.html">gtk+</ulink> (version &gt;= 3.0)</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>(Optional: --with-at-spi configure option) <ulink url="http://ftp.gnome.org/pub/gnome/sources/at-spi/">cspi</ulink> (version &gt;= 2.0)</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para><ulink url="http://ftp.gnome.org/pub/gnome/sources/libxml2/">libxml</ulink> (версии &gt;= 2.0)</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para><ulink url="http://ftp.gnome.org/pub/GNOME/sources/librsvg/">librsvg</ulink></para></listitem>
			<listitem><para><ulink url="http://www.gnu.org/software/gettext/">Получить текст</ulink></para></listitem>
			<listitem><para><ulink url="http://ftp.gnome.org/pub/GNOME/sources/intltool">intltool</ulink> (версии &gt;= 0.23)</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para><ulink url="http://gstreamer.freedesktop.org">gstreamer</ulink> (version &gt; 1.0)</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>(Опционально: --with-docs конфигурирует опции) <ulink url="http://ftp.gnome.org/pub/GNOME/sources/gnome-doc-utils">gnome-doc-utils</ulink></para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>(Опционально: --with-libnotify конфигурирует опции) <ulink url="http://www.galago-project.org/files/releases/source/libnotify">libnotify</ulink></para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>(Опционально: --with-xtst конфигурирует опции) <ulink url="http://xorg.freedesktop.org/releases/individual/lib/">libxtst</ulink></para></listitem>
		</orderedlist>
		<para>How to install those dependencies is dependant on your distribution. If you don't know how to install them, please check with your distribution support.</para>
	</sect2>
	<sect2 id="from-source">
		<title>From source</title>
		<para>Installing Florence from source is like installing any program that uses the GNU autotools. Open a terminal and type the following commands:</para>
		<screen>
<prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>tar -xjvf florence-0.6.3.tar.bz2</userinput>
<prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>cd florence-0.6.3</userinput>
<prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>./configure --prefix=/usr</userinput>
<prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>make</userinput>
<prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>su -c "make install"</userinput>
		</screen>
		<para>Для Ubuntu, заменить последнюю команду на:</para><screen><prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>sudo make install</userinput></screen>
		<para>Проверьте список других настраиваемых опций, совместимых с:</para>
		<screen>
<prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>./configure --help</userinput>
		</screen>
	</sect2>
	<sect2 id="binary-install">
		<title>From distribution package</title>
		<para>Your distribution may already have a recent binary package of Florence. In this case, you don't have to build it from source.</para>
		<orderedlist>
			<listitem>
				<para><ulink url="http://www.redhat.com">Red Hat</ulink>/<ulink url="http://www.centos.org">CentOS</ulink>/<ulink url="http://fedoraproject.org/">Fedora</ulink>
				<screen>
<prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>su - root</userinput>
<prompt>#</prompt> <userinput>yum install florence</userinput>
				</screen></para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para><ulink url="http://openmandriva.org/">OpenMandriva</ulink>/<ulink url="https://www.mageia.org/">Mageia</ulink>
				<screen>
<prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>su - root</userinput>
<prompt>#</prompt> <userinput>urpmi florence</userinput>
				</screen></para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para><ulink url="http://www.debian.org/">Debian</ulink>
				<screen>
<prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>su - root</userinput>
<prompt>№</prompt> <userinput>apt-get install florence</userinput>
				</screen></para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para><ulink url="http://www.ubuntu.com/">Ubuntu</ulink>
				<screen>
<prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>sudo apt-get install florence</userinput>
				</screen></para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>Other distributions : check with your distribution support.</para>
			</listitem>
		</orderedlist>
	</sect2>
	<sect2>
		<title>Uninstall (from source)</title>
		<para>Uninstalling is as easy as installing. If you installed from source, you can uninstall with the following commands:</para>
		<screen>
<prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>cd florence-0.6.3</userinput>
<prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>su -c "make uninstall"</userinput>
		</screen>
		<para>Для Ubuntu:</para><screen><prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>sudo make uninstall</userinput></screen>
	</sect2>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="usage">
	<title>Использовано</title>
	<para>Florence запускается легко. Чтобы запустить Florence из командной строки, выполните:</para>
		<screen>
<prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>florence</userinput>
		</screen>
		<para>From a <ulink url="http://mate-desktop.org/">MATE desktop</ulink>, you can launch Florence from the menu <guimenu>Applications</guimenu>-&gt;<guisubmenu>Accessibility</guisubmenu>-&gt;<guimenuitem>Florence Virtual keyboard</guimenuitem>.
		If you prefer that Florence is launched at MATE startup, choose the menu item <guimenu>System</guimenu>-&gt;<guisubmenu>Preferences</guisubmenu>-&gt;<guimenuitem>Sessions</guimenuitem>, click on the <guibutton>Startup programs</guibutton> tab, then click <guibutton>Add</guibutton> and enter <command>/usr/bin/florence</command> so Florence is launched with MATE at next boot.
	</para>
	<para>Когда включён Florence, иконка должны находиться в зоне уведомлений, обычно справа сверху экрана. Клик по иконке убирает или включает видимость Florence на экране. Щелчком правой кнопкой мыши на нём вызывается меню. В этом меню вы можете использовать <guimenuitem>quit</guimenuitem>, чтобы выйти из Florence.</para>
	<sect2 id="input_methods">
		<title>Методы ввода</title>
		<para>Florence can be used with 4 different input methods. Each method has advantages and drawbacks. It is up to you to select the right one for your usage pattern.</para>
		<orderedlist>
			<listitem>
				<para>The default input method is the "mouse" method. This is adapted for mouse/trackpad input. It is pretty straightforward. Just click on the key with a mouse button to press it. Release the mouse button to release the key. The advantage of this method is its simplicity. It does not require learning. The drawback is that is requires a pointing device with a button and that the user is able to use it.</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>The second input method is the "touch" method. This is adapted for touch screen input. The difference with the mouse input method is that it not possible to touch the keyboard without clicking. In this mode, the keys are pressed on touch end.</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>The next method is the "timer" method. Use this method if you are unable to use a button. Point a key with the pointer and a timer is triggered. When the timer expires, the key is pressed and immediately released. The timer is cancelled if the pointer leaves the key. Note you can still press a mouse button to activate the key if you have one available. The advantage of this method is that it does not require a button. The drawbacks are that it is slower than the button method and that you can not hold a key pressed.</para>	
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>The last method is the "ramble" method. Like the timer method, the ramble method does not require a button. This method can be faster than the timer method but requires dexterity and training to be used efficiently. The ramble method can be passive: no button necessary, or active: deaf while the pointer button is not pressed. There are two sub-methods for rambling.</para>
				<orderedlist>
					<listitem>
						<para>The time-based ramble method requires good timing. While you move the pointer, Florence will detect keys that are to be activated based on the time the pointer stays over them. With this method, you can press the same key multiple times by moving the pointer to near the border of the key and back to the center. This method can be pretty fast with good training.</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>The distance-based ramble method requires some dexterity to be used efficiently. The distance the pointer moves over the key is measured and the key is activated when it reaches a threshold. The key can be pressed multiple times by moving the pointer over the key repeatedly. A second threshold is there to detect multiple occurences. To use this method efficiently, apply quick gestures over the keys you want to activate.</para>
					</listitem>
				</orderedlist>
			</listitem>
		</orderedlist>
	</sect2>
	<sect2 id="modes">
		<title>Режимы Florence</title>
		<para>Florence работает в нескольких режимах, влияющих на его функционал и использование пользователем.</para>
		<para>В режиме автоскрытия Florence сворачивается, когда в нём нет необходимости. Есть несколько правил, чтобы понять, когда Florence должен быть запущен. Они описаны в <ulink url="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/AT-SPI">at-spi</ulink>. Например, Florence появляется, когда вы наведёте курсор на редактируемый виджет, который настроен при использовании клавиатуры. Florence будет скрыт, когда курсор убран с виджета. Это не работает, если виджет на совместим с <ulink url="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/AT-SPI">at-spi</ulink>. В частности, виджеты QT3 не будут стабильно работать с Florence. Вы должны быть уверены, что ваши приложения поддерживают at-spi, если вы намереваетесь использовать Florence в скрытом режиме. Когда этот режим отключён, Florence всегда виден на экране.</para>
		<para>The auto hide mode requires accessibility to be activated, which means the at-spi registry daemon is running and applications are using it.</para>
		<figure id="extensions">
			<title>Расширения Florence</title>
			<screenshot>
				<mediaobject>
					<imageobject><imagedata fileref="figures/florence.png" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
					<textobject><phrase>Показывает доступные расширения</phrase></textobject>
				</mediaobject>
			</screenshot>
		</figure>
		<para>На рисунке выше показаны различные части раскладки по умолчанию. Там же показаны другие раскладки, которые могут быть выбраны в окне настройки (раздел раскладок).</para>
		<para>The default keyboard layout can be extended with 4 extensions to the core keyboard. The Florence key pad is an extension to the left of the main keyboard which contains keys to access special Florence functions: see below for a complete list of Florence functions. The arrows keypad is an extension added to the right of the core keyboard and contains the arrow keys along with navigation keys. The numpad extension contains the numeric keys and the function keys extension contains the function keys. Each extension can be activated and deactivated independantly. The extensions are relative to the selected layout.</para>
	</sect2>
	<sect2 id="florencekeys">
		<title>Florence keys</title>
		<para>The following keys give access to special Florence functions. They are located on the "Florence keys" extension.</para>
		<para><figure id="minimize">
			<title>Minimize key</title>
			<mediaobject>
				<imageobject><imagedata fileref="figures/minimize.png" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
				<textobject><phrase>Minimize key.</phrase></textobject>
			</mediaobject>
		</figure>The minimize key hides the keyboard. The program is still running and the keyboard can be shown again by clicking on the icon or by selecting a text entry widget when auto-hide mode is on.</para>
		<para><figure id="configuration">
			<title>Configuration key</title>
			<mediaobject>
				<imageobject><imagedata fileref="figures/configuration.png" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
				<textobject><phrase>Configuration key.</phrase></textobject>
			</mediaobject>
		</figure>The configuration key opens the configuration dialog. See the configuration chapter for more information about the configuration dialog.</para>
		<para><figure id="move">
			<title>Move key</title>
			<mediaobject>
				<imageobject><imagedata fileref="figures/move.png" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
				<textobject><phrase>Move key.</phrase></textobject>
			</mediaobject>
		</figure>You can move the keyboard around the screen with the move key. Press the move key, move the pointer and release the button when the keyboard is located where you want it.</para>
		<para><figure id="bigger">
			<title>Bigger key</title>
			<mediaobject>
				<imageobject><imagedata fileref="figures/bigger.png" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
				<textobject><phrase>Bigger key.</phrase></textobject>
			</mediaobject>
		</figure>Press the bigger key to increase the size of the keyboard.</para>
		<para><figure id="smaller">
			<title>Smaller key</title>
			<mediaobject>
				<imageobject><imagedata fileref="figures/smaller.png" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
				<textobject><phrase>Smaller key.</phrase></textobject>
			</mediaobject>
		</figure>Press the smaller key to decrease the size of the keyboard.</para>
		<para><figure id="close">
			<title>Close key</title>
			<mediaobject>
				<imageobject><imagedata fileref="figures/close.png" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
				<textobject><phrase>Close key.</phrase></textobject>
			</mediaobject>
		</figure>Press the close key to terminate the program. The close key is accessible when the alt modifier key is pressed, at the location of the minimize key.</para>
		<para><figure id="switch">
			<title>Switch key</title>
			<mediaobject>
				<imageobject><imagedata fileref="figures/switch.png" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
				<textobject><phrase>Switch key.</phrase></textobject>
			</mediaobject>
	</figure>The switch key is accessible when the alt modifier key is pressed, at the location of the configuration key. The label of the key shows the current language of the keyboard. Press it to switch to the next laguage. Pressing it several times cycles through the available language layouts. On GNOME/MATE, the available language layouts can be configured with the <command>gnome-keyboard-properties</command> program (in the layout tab). If only one language is configured, pressing this key has no effect, it just shows the language layout currently configured.</para>
	</sect2>
	<sect2 id="modifiers">
		<title>Клавиши-модификаторы</title>
		<para>Некоторые клавиши имеют модификатор, как на обычной клавиатуре. Когда клавиша нажата, выполняется другое действие, нежели на обычной клавише. Управляют включением модификации клавиши SHIFT и CAPS LOCK. Это - два разных типа клавиш-модификаторов: блокированный и неблокированный типы модификаторов. Блокированный тип активируется, когда кнопка нажата и деактивируется, когда кнопка нажата ещё раз. Неблокированный тип активирован только когда кнопка нажата.</para>
		<para>When activated, the locker keys turn red (the color can be changed in the settings dialog) and the symbol displayed on all non-modifier keys is changed accordingly. If a non-modifier key is pressed while a locker key is active, its effect will be modified according to it.</para>
		<para>When using a mouse, it is not possible to press 2 keys at the same time. As a solution to this problem, Florence latches non-locker modifiers when pressed. When a modifier is latched, it turns green (that color can be changed in the settings dialog). It will remain latched until another non-modifier key is pressed. If a latched key is pressed again, it turns red and becomes locked. A locked modifier will remain locked until it is pressed again to become released.</para>
	</sect2>
	<sect2 id="config">
		<title>Configuration</title>
		<para>The configuration dialog is accessible via the system tray and floating icon (right click on it and select <guimenuitem>Preferences</guimenuitem>) or via the command line with the -c or --config switch: <command>florence --config</command> or via the configuration button on the keyboard if present. Hacking configuration is possible via dconf (see the hacking section)</para>
		<para>Некоторые выбранные опции не будут применены, пока вы не нажмёте "Применить". Некоторые другие опции применяются сразу, но могут быть отменены нажатием кнопки "Отмена", если вы перед этим не применили изменения.</para>
		<para>Настраиваемые опции разделены на четыре группы для более лучшего понимания и поиска между ними.</para>
		<sect3><title>Конфигурировать стиль</title>
		<figure id="style">
			<title>Диалог настроек стиля</title>
			<screenshot>
				<mediaobject>
					<imageobject><imagedata fileref="figures/style.png" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
					<textobject><phrase>Показывает диалог настройки стиля.</phrase></textobject>
				</mediaobject>
			</screenshot>
		</figure>
		<para>Следующие опции стиля могут быть настроены:</para>
		<orderedlist>
			<listitem><para>Стиль: выберите ваш стиль, нажав на иконку стиля.</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>Цвет кнопок по умолчанию: выбор цвета обычных кнопок.</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>Цвет заблокированных кнопок: выбор цвета недоступных к использованию кнопок.</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>Цвет нажатых кнопок: выбор цвета нажатых или заблокированных кнопок.</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>Цвет сфокусированной кнопки: выбор цвета клавиши, на которой находится курсор.</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>Цвет символов: выбор цвета текста на клавишах.</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>Цвет краёв: выбор цвета окаймления букв. Используется для улучшения видимости символов на кнопках. Должен быть более контрастным, нежели цвет самого символа.</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>Увеличение фокуса: установка масштаба "лупы". Полезно для людей с нарушением зрения.</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>Enable sound: when this box is checked, the keyboard generates sound feedback when a key is hovered, pressed or released.</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>Use system font: when this box is checked, the labels on the keys use the default system font. When this box is unchecked, the font selected below is used instead.</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>Keyboard font: With this parameter you can select the font used to draw key labels and its size.</para></listitem>
		</orderedlist>
		</sect3><sect3><title>Настройка окна</title>
		<figure id="window">
			<title>Диалог настройки окна.</title>
			<screenshot>
				<mediaobject>
					<imageobject><imagedata fileref="figures/window.png" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
					<textobject><phrase>Показывает диалог настроек окна.</phrase></textobject>
				</mediaobject>
			</screenshot>
		</figure>
		<orderedlist>
			<listitem><para>Декорирование: украшает окно и заголовок. Делает перетаскивание окна более удобным.</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>Прозрачность: позволяет вам видеть окна под клавиатурой и щёлкать по ним.</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>Масштаб: позволяет вам настроить величину клавиатуры. Некоторые менеджеры окон требуют включения декора окна, чтобы масштабировать окно.</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>Панель задач: сделать Florence видимым на панели задач.</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>Всегда наверху: держит окно с клавиатурой всегда поверх всех окон.</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>System tray icon: Display an icon in the system tray to control the keyboard: you can right-click on it to display the Florence menu and left-click on it to show or hide the keybaord.</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>Floating icon: Like the system tray icon but not attached to the system tray. You can drag the icon around the screen to move it where you want it.</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>Opacity: set the window opacity in order to see the other windows through the keys. The window manager must support compositing and it must be activated for this option to work.</para></listitem>
		</orderedlist>
		</sect3><sect3><title>Настройка поведения</title>
		<figure id="behaviour">
			<title>Диалог настройки поведения</title>
			<screenshot>
				<mediaobject>
					<imageobject><imagedata fileref="figures/behaviour.png" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
					<textobject><phrase>Показывает диалог настройки поведения</phrase></textobject>
				</mediaobject>
			</screenshot>
		</figure>
		<orderedlist>
			<listitem><para>Метод ввода: устанавливает метод ввода. Некоторые методы ввода могут иметь дополнительные опции.</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>Автоскрытие: включает или выключает автоскрытие окна.</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>Перемещение к выбраному виджету: эта опция доступна только когда автоскрытие включено. Когда влючено, клавиатура будет перемещена к ближайшему выбранному виджету каждый раз, когда вы выберите другой, с целью уменьшить расстояние от указателя до клавиатуры.</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>Intermediate icon: In auto-hide mode, don't show the keyboard directly on editable widgets, but make an intermediate icon appear instead. Click on the intermediate icon to show the actual keyboard. This option makes Florence less intrusive: for instance, if you want to read a document without editing, the intermediate icon takes less screen space than the keyboard.</para></listitem>
		</orderedlist>
		</sect3><sect3><title>Настройка раскладок</title>
		<figure id="layout">
			<title>Диалог настройки раскладок</title>
			<screenshot>
				<mediaobject>
					<imageobject><imagedata fileref="figures/layout.png" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
					<textobject><phrase>Показывает диалог настройки раскладок.</phrase></textobject>
				</mediaobject>
			</screenshot>
		</figure>
		<para>Первый комбобокс позволяет вам выбрать вашу раскладку клавиатуры. К раскладке также могут быть применены расширения. Они могут быть включены или выключены независимо друг от друга. Ниже приведены четыре расширения для стандартной раскладки:</para>
		<orderedlist>
			<listitem><para>Клавиши навигации: включить или выключить стрелки.</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>Цифровые клавиши: включение или выключение Num-клавиатуры.</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>Функциональные клавиши: включение или выключение расширенных функциональных клавиш.</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>Клавиши действия: включить/выключить расширение клавиш действия.</para></listitem>
		</orderedlist>
		</sect3>
	</sect2>
	<sect2>
		<title>Параметры командной строки</title>
		<synopsis>florence [OPTION] ... [COMMAND] [ARG]</synopsis>
		<para>The <command>florence</command> command accepts the following options:</para>
		<orderedlist>
			<listitem><para>-h (--help): показывает краткую помощь и закрывает программу.</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>-V (--version): показывает установленную версию Florence и закрывает программу.</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>-c (--config): открывает окно настроек.</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>-d (--debug): запускает Florence с дебаггером.</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>-f (--focus) [window]: with this option, any florence input will go to the selected window. The window argument is the name of the window (the one that most window managers put in the title bar). if the window argument is not provided, florence will select the last focused window. This option is useful for window managers that don't support the 'not focusable' hint and focus the keyboard window instead of the output one. It can also be useful if you want to input text to a window that is not focused. This option must be used for the keyboard to work in GDM.</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>-u (--use-config) file: use the configuration file provided instead of dconf. The configuration file is a key-value pair file with sections. An example of configuration file is provided at /usr/share/florence/florence.conf (the path may be changed with the --prefix configure option).</para></listitem>
		</orderedlist>
		<para>The following commands are available to control the keyboard from a script:</para>
		<orderedlist>
			<listitem><para>show : show the keyboard.</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>hide : hide the keyboard.</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>move x,y : move the keyboard at x,y position on the screen.</para></listitem>
		</orderedlist>
	</sect2>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="how-to">
	<title>How to</title>
	<para>This section provides guides to achieve some common tasks.</para>
	<sect2 id="auto-hide">
		<title>Activating auto-hide mode</title>
		<para>For auto-hide mode to work, you need to start the at-spi registry daemon at session startup. Usually, the daemon executable us located at <filename class="directory">/usr/libexec</filename>. Start at-spi registry daemon (at session startup):</para>
		<screen>
<prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>/usr/libexec/at-spi-registryd &amp;</userinput>
		</screen>
		<para>Некоторые дистрибутивы могут содержать команду at-spi-registryd в другом месте. Используйте команду поиска, чтобы найти местоположение at-spi-registryd:</para>
		<screen>
<prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>find /usr -name at-spi-registryd</userinput>
		</screen>
		<para>When the at-spi registry daemon is started, you need to tell applications to use it.</para>
		<para>For gtk3 applications, you can set on the dconf property org.gnome.desktop.interface.toolkit-accessibility with <command>dconf-editor</command> or you can set the environment variable GTK_MODULES to gail:atk-bridge in /etc/environment, /etc/profile.d or wherever your distro will interpret it at startup.</para>
		<screen>
<prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>export GTK_MODULES=gail:atk-bridge</userinput>
		</screen>
		<para>For java applications, you need to install the java access bridge. On Debian, you can do that with this command:</para>
		<screen>
<prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>sudo apt-get install libaccess-bridge-java</userinput>
		</screen>
		<para>Other distributions should have a similar package available. Please check with your distribution support.</para>
		<para>For QT4 applications, you need to install the <ulink url="https://projects.kde.org/projects/playground/accessibility/qtatspi">qt-at-spi</ulink> package. On debian, use this command:</para>
		<screen>
<prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>sudo apt-get install qt-at-spi</userinput>
		</screen>
		<para>QT5 applications should work out of the box as the at-spi bridge has been merged into QtBase.</para>
		<para>For other toolkits, please check the available documentation and support.</para>
		<para><ulink url="http://mate-desktop.org/">MATE</ulink> starts the daemon automatically if it is configured with the <command>mate-at-property</command> dialog.</para>
		<para>Other desktop environments may setup at-spi automatically for you. Check your desktop documentation for more information.</para>
		<para>When at-spi is properly configured in your desktop environment, you can tell Florence to use the auto-hide mode.</para>
		<screen>
<prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>florence --config</userinput>
		</screen>
		<para>Note that QT3 applications don't support at-spi. Therefore you should not activate auto-hide mode on KDE3.</para>
	</sect2>
	<sect2 id="login-gdm2">
		<title>Using Florence at login with GDM2</title>
		<para>Using florence at GDM 2 is possible with gdmlogin. gdmgreeter has some issues with accessibility.</para>
		<para>Настройка GDM к запуску Florence при входе включает в себя два файла в /etc/X11/gdm (требует привилегий root): custom.conf и modules/AccessKeyMouseEvents.</para>
		<para>В /etc/X11/gdm/custom.conf добавьте следующие строки в секции [daemon] (если они ещё не готовы):</para>
		<programlisting>
Greeter=/usr/lib/gdmlogin 
GtkModulesList=gail:atk-bridge:/usr/lib/gtk-2.0/modules/libkeymouselistener:/usr/lib/gtk-2.0/modules/libdwellmouselistener
		</programlisting>
		<para>В /etc/X11/gdm/modules/AccessKeyMouseEvents добавьте следующие строки:</para>
		<programlisting>
# Запуск Florence посредством нажатия и удержания любой кнопки мыши более двух секунд
&lt;Mouse1&gt; 1 2000 10000 /usr/bin/florence --focus --no-gnome --use-config /usr/share/florence/florence.conf
&lt;Mouse2&gt; 1 2000 10000 /usr/bin/florence --focus --no-gnome --use-config /usr/share/florence/florence.conf
&lt;Mouse3&gt; 1 2000 10000 /usr/bin/florence --focus --no-gnome --use-config /usr/share/florence/florence.conf
		</programlisting>
		<para>Вы должны удалить любые другие строки, начинающиеся с &lt;mouse1&gt;, &lt;mouse2&gt; или &lt;mouse3&gt; для того, чтобы предотвратить запуск любой другой клавиатуры при старте вместе с Florence (например, gok).</para>
		<para>When you have edited those two files, you should be able to start florence at next boot at gdm login. Press any mouse button for more than 2 seconds at the login window to do so.</para>
		<para>Вы также можете настраивать параметры клавиатуры в GDM посредством этой команды (под root):</para>
		<screen>
<prompt>№</prompt> <userinput>florence -c --use-config /usr/share/florence/florence.conf</userinput>
		</screen>
	</sect2>
	<sect2 id="login-gdm3">
		<title>Using Florence at login with GDM3</title>
		<para>With GDM3, it is very simple to use Florence at login screen. On Debian, you can use this command:</para>
		<screen>
<prompt>№</prompt> <userinput>cp /usr/share/applications/florence.desktop /usr/share/gdm/autostart/LoginWindow/</userinput>
		</screen>
		<para>This should work on other distributions as well, although the pathes may be slightly different.</para>
	</sect2>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="faq">
	<title>FAQ (часто задаваемые вопросы)</title>
	<qandaset defaultlabel="qanda">
		<qandaentry>
			<question>
				<para>Does Florence support international keyboard layouts with non-European characters (such as Arab, Chinese, Punjab, etc...)</para>
			</question>
			<answer>
				<para>Yes. Florence does support all the keyboard layouts supported by X. In order to use a different keyboard layout, you can use the setxkbmap command. For instance, to use an Arabic keyboard, use the following command:</para>
		<screen>
<prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>setxkbmap ar</userinput>
		</screen>
				<para>Это работает с любым языком, который поддерживает Xorg</para>
				<para>Some desktop environments also provide a dialog to change the keyboard layout, like <ulink url="http://mate-desktop.org/">MATE</ulink>'s <command>mate-keyboard-properties</command>.</para>
				<para>You can configure several language layouts in <command>mate-keyboard-properties</command>. There are several applets that allow you to easily change layout. You can also change layout in Florence: press Alt and the config key in the "action keys" extension. This will switch to the next language configured in mate-keyboard-properties.</para>	
			</answer>
		</qandaentry>
		<qandaentry>
			<question>
				<para>Моя раскладка мне не подходит. Могу ли я сменить её?</para>
			</question>
			<answer>
				<para>Да. Вы можете изменить раскладку в диалоге настроек (вкладка "раскладки"). Вы также можете сделать собственную раскладку (смотрите <link linkend="hacking">секцию взлома</link> этой документации).</para>
			</answer>
		</qandaentry>
	</qandaset>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="hacking">
	<title>Hacking</title>
	<para>Some extra configuration options are available in dconf (under apps/florence). You can modify configuration parameters from <command>dconf-editor</command>. Each configuration element has a detailed description available.</para>
	<sect2>
		<title>Create your own layout</title>
		<para>It is possible to create your own keyboard layout if those available by default are not suitable for your needs.</para>
		<para>An editor is available in the git repository of Florence, although it is not suitable for release yet. It is not very stable and not documented yet but you can still try it. Fetch it with this command:</para>
		<screen>
<prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>git clone git://git.code.sf.net/p/florence/code/editor florence-editor</userinput>
		</screen>
		<para>Then you can launch the editor with this command:</para>
		<screen>
<prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>python florence-editor/editor.py</userinput>
		</screen>
	</sect2>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="alternatives">
	<title>Alternatives</title>
	<para>There are other alternative virtual keyboard for X that may fit your needs better than Florence. Here is a list of the main keyboard alternatives.</para>
	<orderedlist>
		<listitem><para><ulink url="http://www.gok.ca/gok">GOK</ulink> is the default GNOME onscreen keyboard. It provides more features than Florence for disabled people. It can be used with special devices like switches and joysticks. GOK provides complete access to the desktop. It can be used to move and resize windows and to use any widget. It is application aware and provides a predictive dictionary that make it an effcient keyboard. It is more focussed on accessibility than on aestetics. The high number of features makes it more complex. Florence is arguably prettier and easier to use for people who can easily use a pointing device. GOK is the only option for disabled people who can't use a pointing device.</para></listitem>
		<listitem><para><ulink url="http://homepage3.nifty.com/tsato/xvkbd">XVKBD</ulink> is a simple and very mature virtual keyboard. It does not depend on GNOME. Like GOK, it provides word completion. Like Florence, it has an auto-click feature but it lacks an auto-hide mode and does not integrate with GNOME as much as Florence. This is the perfect keyboard for simple window managers. Florence is arguably prettier and better integrated in GNOME.</para></listitem>
		<listitem><para><ulink url="https://launchpad.net/onboard">Onboard</ulink> is the default Ubuntu keyboard. It runs with python, which is common in modern linux distributions. It focuses on simplicity rather than features. It is pretty and easy to use. It is less customizable than Florence and does not provide an auto-hide feature. Perfect for casual usage on Ubuntu.</para></listitem>
	</orderedlist>
	<table>
		<title>Keyboards features</title>
		<tgroup cols="6">
			<colspec colname="keyboard"/>
			<colspec colname="transparency"/>
			<colspec colname="auto hide"/>
			<colspec colname="auto click"/>
			<colspec colname="scanning"/>
			<colspec colname="word completion"/>
			<thead>
				<row>
					<entry>keyboard</entry>
					<entry>transparency</entry>
					<entry>auto hide</entry>
					<entry>auto click</entry>
					<entry>scanning</entry>
					<entry>word completion</entry>
				</row>
			</thead>
			<tbody>
				<row>
					<entry>Florence</entry>
					<entry>Yes</entry>
					<entry>Yes</entry>
					<entry>Yes</entry>
					<entry>No</entry>
					<entry>No</entry>
				</row>
				<row>
					<entry>GOK</entry>
					<entry>No</entry>
					<entry>Yes</entry>
					<entry>Yes</entry>
					<entry>Yes</entry>
					<entry>Yes</entry>
				</row>
				<row>
					<entry>XVKBD</entry>
					<entry>No</entry>
					<entry>No</entry>
					<entry>Yes</entry>
					<entry>No</entry>
					<entry>Yes</entry>
				</row>
				<row>
					<entry>Onboard</entry>
					<entry>No</entry>
					<entry>No</entry>
					<entry>Yes</entry>
					<entry>No</entry>
					<entry>No</entry>
				</row>
			</tbody>
		</tgroup>
	</table>
	<para>There are other non-keyboard alternatives that can be used to input text.</para>
	<orderedlist>
		<listitem>
			<para><ulink url="http://www.inference.phy.cam.ac.uk/dasher">Dasher</ulink> provides a predictive gesture based method to input text. This is a very efficient and natural input method. It can be used to input text only with eye movements when combined with <ulink url="http://www.inference.phy.cam.ac.uk/opengazer">opengazer</ulink></para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<para><ulink url="http://risujin.org/cellwriter/">CellWriter</ulink> is a hand writing recognition tool. It is a good text input method for tablets. CellWriter also provides a virtual keyboard.</para>
		</listitem>
	</orderedlist>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="gethelp">
        <title>Getting help</title>
        <para>You can get help on the <ulink url="https://sourceforge.net/forum/forum.php?forum_id=784280">forum</ulink>, or you can ask for help by email at f.agrech@gmail.com</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="help">
	<title>Contribute</title>
	<para>If you want to help the Florence project, please send an email to f.agrech@gmail.com</para>
</sect1>
<appendix id="gfdl">
  <title>GNU Free Documentation License</title>
  <para>
    Copyright (C) 2000, 2001, 2002 Free Software Foundation,
    <abbrev>Inc.</abbrev> 51 Franklin <abbrev>St</abbrev>, Fifth Floor,
    Boston, <abbrev>MA</abbrev> 02110-1301 <abbrev role="initialism">USA</abbrev>.  Everyone is permitted to copy and
    distribute verbatim copies of this license document, but changing it is
    not allowed.
  </para>
  <bridgehead id="Preamble" renderas="sect1">
    0. PREAMBLE
  </bridgehead>
  <para>
    The purpose of this License is to make a manual, textbook, or other
    functional and useful document "free" in the sense of freedom: to assure
    everyone the effective freedom to copy and redistribute it, with or
    without modifying it, either commercially or noncommercially.
    Secondarily, this License preserves for the author and publisher a way to
    get credit for their work, while not being considered responsible for
    modifications made by others.
  </para>
  <para>
    This License is a kind of "copyleft", which means that derivative works of
    the document must themselves be free in the same sense.  It complements
    the GNU General Public License, which is a copyleft license designed for
    free software.
  </para>
  <para>
    We have designed this License in order to use it for manuals for free
    software, because free software needs free documentation: a free program
    should come with manuals providing the same freedoms that the software
    does.  But this License is not limited to software manuals; it can be used
    for any textual work, regardless of subject matter or whether it is
    published as a printed book.  We recommend this License principally for
    works whose purpose is instruction or reference.</para>
  <bridgehead id="Definitions" renderas="sect1">
    1. APPLICABILITY AND DEFINITIONS
  </bridgehead>
  <para>
    This License applies to any manual or other work, in any medium, that
    contains a notice placed by the copyright holder saying it can be
    distributed under the terms of this License.  Such a notice grants a
    world-wide, royalty-free license, unlimited in duration, to use that work
    under the conditions stated herein.  The "Document", below, refers to any
    such manual or work.  Any member of the public is a licensee, and is
    addressed as "you".  You accept the license if you copy, modify or
    distribute the work in a way requiring permission under copyright
    law.
  </para>
  <para>
    A "Modified Version" of the Document means any work containing the
    Document or a portion of it, either copied verbatim, or with modifications
    and/or translated into another language.
  </para>
  <para>
    A "Secondary Section" is a named appendix or a front-matter section of the
    Document that deals exclusively with the relationship of the publishers or
    authors of the Document to the Document's overall subject (or to related
    matters) and contains nothing that could fall directly within that overall
    subject.  (Thus, if the Document is in part a textbook of mathematics, a
    Secondary Section may not explain any mathematics.)  The relationship
    could be a matter of historical connection with the subject or with
    related matters, or of legal, commercial, philosophical, ethical or
    political position regarding them.
  </para>
  <para>
    The "Invariant Sections" are certain Secondary Sections whose titles are
    designated, as being those of Invariant Sections, in the notice that says
    that the Document is released under this License.  If a section does not
    fit the above definition of Secondary then it is not allowed to be
    designated as Invariant.  The Document may contain zero Invariant
    Sections.  If the Document does not identify any Invariant Sections then
    there are none.
  </para>
  <para>
    The "Cover Texts" are certain short passages of text that are listed, as
    Front-Cover Texts or Back-Cover Texts, in the notice that says that the
    Document is released under this License.  A Front-Cover Text may be at
    most 5 words, and a Back-Cover Text may be at most 25 words.
  </para>
  <para>
    A "Transparent" copy of the Document means a machine-readable copy,
    represented in a format whose specification is available to the general
    public, that is suitable for revising the document straightforwardly with
    generic text editors or (for images composed of pixels) generic paint
    programs or (for drawings) some widely available drawing editor, and that
    is suitable for input to text formatters or for automatic translation to a
    variety of formats suitable for input to text formatters.  A copy made in
    an otherwise Transparent file format whose markup, or absence of markup,
    has been arranged to thwart or discourage subsequent modification by
    readers is not Transparent.  An image format is not Transparent if used
    for any substantial amount of text.  A copy that is not "Transparent" is
    called "Opaque".
  </para>
  <para>
    Examples of suitable formats for Transparent copies include plain ASCII
    without markup, Texinfo input format, LaTeX input format, SGML or XML
    using a publicly available DTD, and standard-conforming simple HTML,
    PostScript or PDF designed for human modification.  Examples of
    transparent image formats include PNG, XCF and JPG.  Opaque formats
    include proprietary formats that can be read and edited only by
    proprietary word processors, SGML or XML for which the DTD and/or
    processing tools are not generally available, and the machine-generated
    HTML, PostScript or PDF produced by some word processors for output
    purposes only.
  </para>
  <para>
    The "Title Page" means, for a printed book, the title page itself, plus
    such following pages as are needed to hold, legibly, the material this
    License requires to appear in the title page.  For works in formats which
    do not have any title page as such, "Title Page" means the text near the
    most prominent appearance of the work's title, preceding the beginning of
    the body of the text.
  </para>
  <para>
    A section "Entitled XYZ" means a named subunit of the Document whose title
    either is precisely XYZ or contains XYZ in parentheses following text that
    translates XYZ in another language.  (Here XYZ stands for a specific
    section name mentioned below, such as "Acknowledgements", "Dedications",
    "Endorsements", or "History".)  To "Preserve the Title" of such a section
    when you modify the Document means that it remains a section "Entitled
    XYZ" according to this definition.
  </para>
  <para>
    The Document may include Warranty Disclaimers next to the notice which
    states that this License applies to the Document.  These Warranty
    Disclaimers are considered to be included by reference in this License,
    but only as regards disclaiming warranties: any other implication that
    these Warranty Disclaimers may have is void and has no effect on the
    meaning of this License.
  </para>
  <bridgehead id="VerbatimCopying" renderas="sect1">
    2. VERBATIM COPYING
  </bridgehead>
  <para>
    You may copy and distribute the Document in any medium, either
    commercially or noncommercially, provided that this License, the copyright
    notices, and the license notice saying this License applies to the
    Document are reproduced in all copies, and that you add no other
    conditions whatsoever to those of this License.  You may not use technical
    measures to obstruct or control the reading or further copying of the
    copies you make or distribute.  However, you may accept compensation in
    exchange for copies.  If you distribute a large enough number of copies
    you must also follow the conditions in section 3.
  </para>
  <para>
    You may also lend copies, under the same conditions stated above, and you
    may publicly display copies.
  </para>
  <bridgehead id="QuantityCopying" renderas="sect1">
    3. COPYING IN QUANTITY
  </bridgehead>
  <para>
    If you publish printed copies (or copies in media that commonly have
    printed covers) of the Document, numbering more than 100, and the
    Document's license notice requires Cover Texts, you must enclose the
    copies in covers that carry, clearly and legibly, all these Cover Texts:
    Front-Cover Texts on the front cover, and Back-Cover Texts on the back
    cover.  Both covers must also clearly and legibly identify you as the
    publisher of these copies.  The front cover must present the full title
    with all words of the title equally prominent and visible.  You may add
    other material on the covers in addition.  Copying with changes limited to
    the covers, as long as they preserve the title of the Document and satisfy
    these conditions, can be treated as verbatim copying in other
    respects.
  </para>
  <para>
    If the required texts for either cover are too voluminous to fit legibly,
    you should put the first ones listed (as many as fit reasonably) on the
    actual cover, and continue the rest onto adjacent pages.
  </para>
  <para>
    If you publish or distribute Opaque copies of the Document numbering more
    than 100, you must either include a machine-readable Transparent copy
    along with each Opaque copy, or state in or with each Opaque copy a
    computer-network location from which the general network-using public has
    access to download using public-standard network protocols a complete
    Transparent copy of the Document, free of added material.  If you use the
    latter option, you must take reasonably prudent steps, when you begin
    distribution of Opaque copies in quantity, to ensure that this Transparent
    copy will remain thus accessible at the stated location until at least one
    year after the last time you distribute an Opaque copy (directly or
    through your agents or retailers) of that edition to the public.
  </para>
  <para>
    It is requested, but not required, that you contact the authors of the
    Document well before redistributing any large number of copies, to give
    them a chance to provide you with an updated version of the
    Document.
  </para>
  <bridgehead id="Modifications" renderas="sect1">
    4. MODIFICATIONS
  </bridgehead>
  <para>
    You may copy and distribute a Modified Version of the Document under the
    conditions of sections 2 and 3 above, provided that you release the
    Modified Version under precisely this License, with the Modified Version
    filling the role of the Document, thus licensing distribution and
    modification of the Modified Version to whoever possesses a copy of it.
    In addition, you must do these things in the Modified Version:
  </para>
  <orderedlist numeration="upperalpha">
    <listitem>
      <simpara>
        Use in the Title Page (and on the covers, if any) a title distinct
        from that of the Document, and from those of previous versions (which
        should, if there were any, be listed in the History section of the
        Document).  You may use the same title as a previous version if the
        original publisher of that version gives permission.
        </simpara>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <simpara>
        List on the Title Page, as authors, one or more persons or entities
        responsible for authorship of the modifications in the Modified
        Version, together with at least five of the principal authors of the
        Document (all of its principal authors, if it has fewer than five),
        unless they release you from this requirement.
      </simpara>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <simpara>
        State on the Title page the name of the publisher of the Modified
        Version, as the publisher.
      </simpara>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <simpara>
        Preserve all the copyright notices of the Document.
      </simpara>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <simpara>
        Add an appropriate copyright notice for your modifications adjacent to
        the other copyright notices.
      </simpara>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <simpara>
        Include, immediately after the copyright notices, a license notice
        giving the public permission to use the Modified Version under the
        terms of this License, in the form shown in the Addendum below.
      </simpara>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <simpara>
        Preserve in that license notice the full lists of Invariant Sections
        and required Cover Texts given in the Document's license notice.
      </simpara>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <simpara>
        Include an unaltered copy of this License.
      </simpara>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <simpara>
        Preserve the section Entitled "History", Preserve its Title, and add
        to it an item stating at least the title, year, new authors, and
        publisher of the Modified Version as given on the Title Page.  If
        there is no section Entitled "History" in the Document, create one
        stating the title, year, authors, and publisher of the Document as
        given on its Title Page, then add an item describing the Modified
        Version as stated in the previous sentence.
      </simpara>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <simpara>
        Preserve the network location, if any, given in the Document for
        public access to a Transparent copy of the Document, and likewise the
        network locations given in the Document for previous versions it was
        based on.  These may be placed in the "History" section.  You may omit
        a network location for a work that was published at least four years
        before the Document itself, or if the original publisher of the
        version it refers to gives permission.
      </simpara>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <simpara>
        For any section Entitled "Acknowledgements" or "Dedications", Preserve
        the Title of the section, and preserve in the section all the
        substance and tone of each of the contributor acknowledgements and/or
        dedications given therein.
      </simpara>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <simpara>
        Preserve all the Invariant Sections of the Document, unaltered in
        their text and in their titles.  Section numbers or the equivalent are
        not considered part of the section titles.
      </simpara>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <simpara>
        Delete any section Entitled "Endorsements".  Such a section may not be
        included in the Modified Version.
      </simpara>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <simpara>
        Do not retitle any existing section to be Entitled "Endorsements" or
        to conflict in title with any Invariant Section.
      </simpara>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <simpara>
        Preserve any Warranty Disclaimers.
      </simpara>
    </listitem>
  </orderedlist>
  <para>
    If the Modified Version includes new front-matter sections or appendices
    that qualify as Secondary Sections and contain no material copied from the
    Document, you may at your option designate some or all of these sections
    as invariant.  To do this, add their titles to the list of Invariant
    Sections in the Modified Version's license notice.  These titles must be
    distinct from any other section titles.
  </para>
  <para>
    You may add a section Entitled "Endorsements", provided it contains
    nothing but endorsements of your Modified Version by various parties--for
    example, statements of peer review or that the text has been approved by
    an organization as the authoritative definition of a standard.
  </para>
  <para>
    You may add a passage of up to five words as a Front-Cover Text, and a
    passage of up to 25 words as a Back-Cover Text, to the end of the list of
    Cover Texts in the Modified Version.  Only one passage of Front-Cover Text
    and one of Back-Cover Text may be added by (or through arrangements made
    by) any one entity.  If the Document already includes a cover text for the
    same cover, previously added by you or by arrangement made by the same
    entity you are acting on behalf of, you may not add another; but you may
    replace the old one, on explicit permission from the previous publisher
    that added the old one.
  </para>
  <para>
    The author(s) and publisher(s) of the Document do not by this License give
    permission to use their names for publicity for or to assert or imply
    endorsement of any Modified Version.
  </para>
  <bridgehead id="Combining" renderas="sect1">
    5. COMBINING DOCUMENTS
  </bridgehead>
  <para>
    You may combine the Document with other documents released under this
    License, under the terms defined in section 4 above for modified versions,
    provided that you include in the combination all of the Invariant Sections
    of all of the original documents, unmodified, and list them all as
    Invariant Sections of your combined work in its license notice, and that
    you preserve all their Warranty Disclaimers.
  </para>
  <para>
    The combined work need only contain one copy of this License, and multiple
    identical Invariant Sections may be replaced with a single copy.  If there
    are multiple Invariant Sections with the same name but different contents,
    make the title of each such section unique by adding at the end of it, in
    parentheses, the name of the original author or publisher of that section
    if known, or else a unique number.  Make the same adjustment to the
    section titles in the list of Invariant Sections in the license notice of
    the combined work.
  </para>
  <para>
    In the combination, you must combine any sections Entitled "History" in
    the various original documents, forming one section Entitled "History";
    likewise combine any sections Entitled "Acknowledgements", and any
    sections Entitled "Dedications".  You must delete all sections Entitled
    "Endorsements".
  </para>
  <bridgehead id="Collections" renderas="sect1">
    6. COLLECTIONS OF DOCUMENTS
  </bridgehead>
  <para>
    You may make a collection consisting of the Document and other documents
    released under this License, and replace the individual copies of this
    License in the various documents with a single copy that is included in
    the collection, provided that you follow the rules of this License for
    verbatim copying of each of the documents in all other respects.
  </para>
  <para>
    You may extract a single document from such a collection, and distribute
    it individually under this License, provided you insert a copy of this
    License into the extracted document, and follow this License in all other
    respects regarding verbatim copying of that document.
  </para>
  <bridgehead id="Aggregation" renderas="sect1">
    7. AGGREGATION WITH INDEPENDENT WORKS
  </bridgehead>
  <para>
    A compilation of the Document or its derivatives with other separate and
    independent documents or works, in or on a volume of a storage or
    distribution medium, is called an "aggregate" if the copyright resulting
    from the compilation is not used to limit the legal rights of the
    compilation's users beyond what the individual works permit.  When the
    Document is included in an aggregate, this License does not apply to the
    other works in the aggregate which are not themselves derivative works of
    the Document.
  </para>
  <para>
    If the Cover Text requirement of section 3 is applicable to these copies
    of the Document, then if the Document is less than one half of the entire
    aggregate, the Document's Cover Texts may be placed on covers that bracket
    the Document within the aggregate, or the electronic equivalent of covers
    if the Document is in electronic form.  Otherwise they must appear on
    printed covers that bracket the whole aggregate.
  </para>
  <bridgehead id="Translation" renderas="sect1">
    8. TRANSLATION
  </bridgehead>
  <para>
    Translation is considered a kind of modification, so you may distribute
    translations of the Document under the terms of section 4.  Replacing
    Invariant Sections with translations requires special permission from
    their copyright holders, but you may include translations of some or all
    Invariant Sections in addition to the original versions of these Invariant
    Sections.  You may include a translation of this License, and all the
    license notices in the Document, and any Warranty Disclaimers, provided
    that you also include the original English version of this License and the
    original versions of those notices and disclaimers.  In case of a
    disagreement between the translation and the original version of this
    License or a notice or disclaimer, the original version will prevail.
  </para>
  <para>
    If a section in the Document is Entitled "Acknowledgements",
    "Dedications", or "History", the requirement (section 4) to Preserve its
    Title (section 1) will typically require changing the actual title.
  </para>
  <bridgehead id="Termination" renderas="sect1">
    9. TERMINATION
  </bridgehead>
  <para>
    You may not copy, modify, sublicense, or distribute the Document except as
    expressly provided for under this License.  Any other attempt to copy,
    modify, sublicense or distribute the Document is void, and will
    automatically terminate your rights under this License.  However, parties
    who have received copies, or rights, from you under this License will not
    have their licenses terminated so long as such parties remain in full
    compliance.
  </para>
  <bridgehead id="FutureRevisions" renderas="sect1">
    10. FUTURE REVISIONS OF THIS LICENSE
  </bridgehead>
  <para>
    The Free Software Foundation may publish new, revised versions of the GNU
    Free Documentation License from time to time.  Such new versions will be
    similar in spirit to the present version, but may differ in detail to
    address new problems or concerns.  See <ulink url="http://www.gnu.org/copyleft/">http://www.gnu.org/copyleft/</ulink>.
  </para>
  <para>
    Each version of the License is given a distinguishing version number.  If
    the Document specifies that a particular numbered version of this License
    "or any later version" applies to it, you have the option of following the
    terms and conditions either of that specified version or of any later
    version that has been published (not as a draft) by the Free Software
    Foundation.  If the Document does not specify a version number of this
    License, you may choose any version ever published (not as a draft) by the
    Free Software Foundation.
  </para>
  <bridgehead id="HowToUse" renderas="sect1">
    ADDENDUM: How to use this License for your documents
  </bridgehead>
  <para>
    To use this License in a document you have written, include a copy of the
    License in the document and put the following copyright and license
    notices just after the title page:
  </para>
  <blockquote>
    <para>
      Copyright (C) YEAR YOUR NAME.
    </para>
    <para>Разрешается копировать, распространять и / или изменение этого документа на условиях лицензии GNU Free Documentation License, версии 1.2 или более поздней версии, опубликованной Free Software Foundation, без неизменяемых разделов, без тексты лицевых обложек, а не назад -заключения. Копия лицензии находится в разделе, озаглавленном "GNU Free Documentation License".</para>
  </blockquote>
  <para>
    If you have Invariant Sections, Front-Cover Texts and Back-Cover Texts,
    replace the "with...Texts." line with this:
  </para>
  <blockquote>
    <para>
      with the Invariant Sections being LIST THEIR TITLES, with the
      Front-Cover Texts being LIST, and with the Back-Cover Texts being LIST.
    </para>
  </blockquote>
  <para>
    If you have Invariant Sections without Cover Texts, or some other
    combination of the three, merge those two alternatives to suit the
    situation.
  </para>
  <para>
    If your document contains nontrivial examples of program code, we
    recommend releasing these examples in parallel under your choice of free
    software license, such as the GNU General Public License, to permit their
    use in free software.
  </para>
</appendix>

</article>
